{"tossups": [{"question": "William Juxon recorded this man's last speech, and John Cook declared the prosecution of this man as fighting \"tyranny itself.\" Some of this man's last words before reaching the Banqueting House were to his children, Henry of Oatlands and Elizabeth Stuart. Colonel Francis Hacker took this man to his death, before which this man cryptically uttered \"remember.\" Either William Hulet or Richard Brandon were responsible for beheading, for ten points, what English king, the only one to be executed?", "answer": "<b><u>Charles I</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Adrastus, King of Argos, vows to never invade this city at the end of the play <em>The</em> <em>Suppliants</em>. This city\u2019s leader, Peisistratus, funded its Dionysia festivals, during which Thespis became the first named man to represent a character on stage. In a namesake play, a resident of this city-state named Lysistrata plots to halt the ongoing Peloponnesian War by convincing Greek wives to stop sleeping with their husbands. For ten points, name this city-state, the home of Aristophanes, whose Theatre of Dionysus was built on its Acropolis.", "answer": "<b><u>Athens</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man became known as the \u201cMarble Model\u201d due to his low number of demerits at West Point and his statuesque demeanor. This man's order to dig ditches around one city led him to be called the \u201cKing of Spades,\u201d and this man's extreme caution in battle led his soldiers to refer to him as \u201cGranny.\u201d During the West Virginia campaign, this man was given the sobriquet \u201cEvacuating\u201d after a defeat at Cheat Mountain. Preceded as a general by his father who was himself nicknamed \u201cLight-Horse,\" for ten points, who was this Confederate Civil War general?", "answer": "<b><u>R</u></b>obert E(dward) <b><u>Lee</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Thomas van Orden challenged the display of the Ten Commandments in this state's Capitol. During the tenure of a governor of this state who also served as Secretary of Energy under Donald Trump, a thirteen-hour filibuster against the anti-abortion Senate Bill 5 was launched by Wendy Davis. In 2021, a senator from this state came under fire for travelling to a Ritz-Carlton in Mexico while over 4.3 million of this state's citizens were without power. Rick Perry and Ted Cruz are both politicians from, for ten points, what U.S. state?", "answer": "<b><u>Texas</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Heather Penney and Marc Sasseville were tasked with thwarting the initial goal of this event, and Mike Pence carries a copy of <em>A Life of Integrity</em> with him when he travels in order to commemorate this event. Resistance from a group of 40 crew members and passengers during this event forced the central vehicle down in Somerset County, Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this event involving the hijacking of a plane that terrorists intended to crash into Washington, D.C, after similar attacks on the Pentagon and the Twin Towers.", "answer": "Hijacking of United Airlines Flight <b><u>93</u></b> (prompt on \"9/11\" attacks; accept synonyms for \"Hijacking\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In this state, the Society for the Suppression of Vice encouraged a police raid of the Everard Baths. Over two dozen men were arrested in this state's anti-gay Ariston Bathhouse raid. This state banned sexual orientation discrimination via the SONDA, and this state legalized same-sex marriage in the Marriage Equality Act in 2011. Dick Leitsch [[LEECH]] led a \"Sip-in\" in this state, and Dave van Ronk was barricaded in a bar during protests in this state's Greenwich Village. For ten points, name this state in which the Stonewall Riots took place.", "answer": "<b><u>New York</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country attempted to overthrow Ra\u00fal Leoni in the Machurucuto Incident in Venezuela. This country, which led Operation Carlota, won the Battle of Quifangondo with the MPLA while fighting South African Defense Forces in Angola. Due to the end of Comecon [[KOH-meh-kohn]], this country faced the <em>Maleconazo</em> protests and shifted to <em>organop\u00f3nicos</em> agriculture during its Special Period. One key leader in the overthrow of this country's Fulgencio Batista was Argentine revolutionary Che Guevara. For ten points, name this Caribbean island nation.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Cuba</u></b> (or Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>Cuba</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A historian from this country was told, \u201cYour criticism of me would damage your reputation as a historian, if you had one\u201d during a 1961 debate. That historian from this country verified that Hitler did not escape Berlin in the late days of the war and controversially claimed that the supposed Hitler Diaries were real. A.J.P. Taylor, who was from this country, created popular television lectures that led to him being compared with this country's Thomas Babington Macaulay. For ten points, name this country in which history broadcasts were run by the BBC.", "answer": "<b><u>United Kingdom</u></b> of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (accept <b><u>UK</u></b>; accept Great <b><u>Britain</u></b>; accept <b><u>England</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1811, this state's \"revolution from above\" freed serfs, allowing peasants to own farmland through the Edict of Regulation. This state was addressed in the 1813 \"To my People\" speech, and Stein and Hardenberg reformed this state, as did Theodor von Sch\u00f6n [[SHUHN]]. This state created Berlin University, where Johann Gottlieb Fichte [[FIK-tuh]] taught. When this state's Queen Louise died, Napoleon claimed the king lost \"his best minister.\" Wilhelm von Humboldt created the new humanism movement in, for ten points, what German kingdom?", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Prussia</u></b> (accept K\u00f6nigreich <b><u>Preussen</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this man's presidency the House launched an investigation into the conduct of General James Wilkinson. This man disapproved of the 1809 Treaty of Fort Wayne, an agreement to purchase Native American land which led to the outbreak of Tecumseh\u2019s War. This man was forced to evacuate the White House due to a British invasion of Washington, D.C. during the War of 1812. For ten points, name this man who succeeded Thomas Jefferson and served as America\u2019s fourth president.", "answer": "James <b><u>Madison</u></b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first person in a family to become one of these people was referred to by a term meaning \u201cnew man.\u201d These people continued to serve under Odoacer [[oh-doh-AH-ker]] before ultimately ceasing to exist in the West in the seventh century. The Gracchi [[GRAH-kee]] weakened the power of these people, whose \u201cultimate decrees\u201d could transfer absolute control to the consul. Usually 300 to 500 of these people served at a time, and they were initially all patricians. Given terms for life, for ten points, who were these Roman legislators?", "answer": "<b><u>Senator</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "One member of this family called in his state\u2019s National Guard to deal with a riot that began after 83 partiers were arrested at a bar on 12th Street. That member of this family criticized a group of companies known as the \u201cBig Three,\u201d calling them \u201cgas-guzzling dinosaurs.\u201d Another of this family's members served as CEO of Bain Capital and claimed to have hired \u201cbinders full of women.\u201d That man from this family replaced Orrin Hatch in the Senate eight years after unsuccessfully running with Paul Ryan for president. For ten points, name this Mormon family which includes George and Mitt.", "answer": "<b><u>Romney</u></b> family (or the <b><u>Romney</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The Della Torre family made a bid to rule this city during the war between the Guelphs [[GWELFS]] and Ghibellines [[GIH-bih-lines]] until their defeat at Desio [[DEH-syoh]]. Following a war of succession in this city, members of the University of Pavia established the short-lived Golden Ambrosian Republic. That republic founded in this city was abolished by the <em>condottiero</em>-turned-duke, Francesco Sforza, who later signed the Peace at Lodi [[LOH-dee]] with Naples and Florence. For ten points, name this northern Italian city, known to the Romans as Mediolanum.", "answer": "<b><u>Milan</u></b> (or <b><u>Milan</u></b>o; accept <b><u>Mediolanum</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A leader from this modern-day country granted William Knox D'Arcy the exclusive right to its oil in a 1901 \"concession.\" A Russian-trained Cossack Brigade assisted Mozaffer ad-Din, a shah of this country's Qajar dynasty. An American named Howard Baskerville was killed during a siege of this country's city of Tabriz, and this country's Pahlavi dynasty was deposed following an Islamic Revolution led by the exiled Ruhollah Khomeini [[koh-MAY-nee]]. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country, formerly called Persia.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of <b><u>Iran</u></b> (accept <b><u>Persia</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this state, a set of six semicircular earthworks constructed by Native Americans form the center of the Poverty Point World Heritage Site. The \"Red River of the South\" once formed part of the U.S.-Mexico border in this state and flows past this state's third-largest city, located mostly in Caddo Parish. This state's Jean Lafitte National Historical Park and Preserve often features reenactments of battles from the War of 1812. For ten points, the French Quarter is the oldest neighborhood of a city in which Mardi Gras is celebrated in what U.S. state?", "answer": "<b><u>Louisiana</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "A lullaby first called \u201cA Time for Tony\u201d inspired the theme song of this program of which Jeff Probst hosted a \"Rock & Roll\" spin-off. Art Fleming was the host of this show when John McCain appeared twice in 1965 but declined Merv Griffin's request to host this program's revival in 1984. In 2003, this program's producers removed a rule limiting contestants to five appearances, enabling a 74-win streak by Ken Jennings. For ten points, name this program which was hosted by Alex Trebek until his death in 2020.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Jeopardy!</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "A secret 1915 treaty signed in this city established Italy as a member of the Allies. An 1839 agreement signed in this city inspired one diplomat to express his disbelief that one country would fight a war over \"a scrap of paper.\" A 1930 conference in this city aimed to update the Washington Naval Treaty signed eight years earlier. Belgian neutrality was affirmed in, for ten points, what capital city of an empire upon which the sun supposedly never set?", "answer": "<b><u>London</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A vice-presidential candidate in this election year claimed that one opponent\u2019s victory would lead to rule by a \u201csemi-barbarous race\u201d who would \u201csubject the white women to their unbridled lust.\" In this election year, Francis P. Blair was the losing vice-presidential candidate on the ticket of Horatio Seymour, who had faced draft riots in New York five years prior. An impeachment was held in this year for violation of the Tenure of Office Act which had passed in the previous year. For ten points, name this election year of the first presidential victory for Ulysses S. Grant.", "answer": "<b><u>1868</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This tribe was the primary audience for Elias Boudinot's</u> </b><em><b><u>Phoenix</u></b></em><b><u> newspaper.</u></b> <b><u>A minority party within this tribe signed the Treaty of New Echota [[eh-KOH-tah]]</u></b> <b><u>that, despite the lack of approval from (*)</u> John Ross, led to an event they called </b><em><b>Nu na </b><b>da ul tsun yi</b></em><b>. Samuel Worcester argued that a law requiring non-natives to have a license to be on land belonging to this tribe was unconstitutional. This tribe rapidly became more (*) </b>literate after Sequoyah created their syllabary. For ten points, name this Native American tribe who were removed from Georgia by way of the Trail of Tears.", "answer": "<b><u>Cherokee</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tsalagi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One woman from what is today this country was named Isabella, known as the</u></b> <b><u>\"First Lady of the World,\" and persuaded Louis XII to not send troops against her</u></b> <b><u>home city. After the Palaiologos started to die out, a cadet branch ruled the March of</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Montferrat in what is now this country. Napoleon defeated an attack under General of the Artillery Joseph Alvinczi, in the Battle of (*) </b>Rivoli in what is now this country. The location of the Rotonda di San Lorenzo of Matilda of Tuscany, for ten points, what is this modern country, the home of Vincenzo II Gonzaga, Duke of Mantua?", "answer": "<b><u>Italy</u></b> (accept <b><u>Italian</u></b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's poetry collections,</u> </b><em><b><u>In the Winter of Cities</u></b></em><b><u> and</u> </b><em><b><u>Androgyne, Mon</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Amour</u></b></em><b><u>, explore his sexuality and his lost childhood as the son of an alcoholic</u></b> <b><u>traveling shoe salesman. This writer's sister, Rose, is thought to be the model for</u></b> <b><u>some of his (+)</u> characters, including Laura Wingfield, and her lobotomy is represented in his work (*) </b><em>Suddenly, Last Summer</em>. Considered one of the greatest American playwrights, for ten points, who was this writer of the Pulitzer Prize-winning works <em>Cat on a Hot Tin Roof</em> and <em>A Streetcar Named Desire</em>?", "answer": "Tennessee <b><u>Williams</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b><u>Le\u00f3n Gieco [[hee-EH-koh]] dedicated a song to this country's outlaws titled</u></b> <b><u>\"Rural Bandits.\" A French-born pirate who fought for this country captured Monterey,</u></b> <b><u>California for six days and was named (+)</u> Hippolyte Bouchard [[ee-poh-LEET boo-SHARD]]. Before he was killed in Bolivia, outlaw Butch Cassidy fled to this country. A folk hero from this country, Juan (*) </b>Moreira, was robbed by a grocery store owner named Sardetti. For ten points, name this South American country known for its gaucho cowboys.", "answer": "<b><u>Argentina</u></b> (accept <b><u>Argentine</u></b> Republic; accept Rep\u00fablica <b><u>Argentina</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b><u>About a thousand people from throughout the Middle East are thought to have</u></b> <b><u>gathered annually at this ancient Mesopotamian site. Scientists have identified the</u></b> <b><u>wild wheat growing around this site as the closest relative to the wheat (+)</u> we eat today, suggesting that celebrations there were a step towards the domestication of crops. Discovered in 1994 by Klaus (*) </b>Schmidt, this site may have been the location of one of the first temples in human history, built between 10,000 and 12,000 years ago. For ten points, name this Neolithic archaeological site in southeastern Turkey.", "answer": "<b><u>G\u00f6bekli Tepe</u> </b> [[gir-BEK-lee TEH-peh]] (or <b><u>Potbelly Hill</u></b>; or <b><u>Gir\u00ea Mirazan</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>A blizzard delayed one army at this battle from commencing its attack on</u></b> <b><u>February 12. A rallying cry at this battle, which echoed a similar cry from the 15th</u></b> <b><u>century, translated to \"we\u2019ll (+)</u> get them.\" Sylvain Raynal\u2019s troops went for days without water at this battle before surrendering Fort Vaux [[VOH]]. The Nivelle Offensive occurred at this battle, at which one side intended to \u201cbleed [the French] white\u201d by forcing counteroffensives. (*) </b>Philippe P\u00e9tain [[peh-TAHN]] became known as the lion of, for ten points, what lengthy World War One battle fought in France?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Verdun</u></b> (accept Bataille de <b><u>Verdun</u></b>; accept Schlacht um <b><u>Verdun</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The western third of this island was ceded from Spain to France in the 1697</u></b> <b><u>Treaty of Ryswick. Leaders of this island's indigenous population, including Hatuey</u></b> <b><u>[[ah-TWAY]], took the title</u> </b><em><b><u>cacique</u></b></em><b><u> [[kah-SEE-keh]]. After (+)</u> Christopher Columbus landed on this island on December 6, 1492, the native Taino [[TIE-noh]] people were divided into five chiefdoms and subjected to slavery. In 1806, troops under General (*) </b>Henri Christophe attempted to seize the entirety of this island from the French. For ten points, name this Caribbean island divided between two countries.", "answer": "<b><u>Hispaniola</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The \"Lavender Scare\" occurred concurrently with an event spearheaded by</u></b> <b><u>this man, who often used homosexuality as a smear tactic in his campaigns. Roy Cohn</u></b> <b><u>was this man's chief counsel during a series of hearings involving this man and the</u></b> <b><u>U.S. (+)</u> Army. The suicide of Senator Lester C. Hunt badly hurt this man's reputation, leading to his (*) </b>censure by the Senate in 1954. For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who is infamous for alleging that Communist spies infiltrated the U.S. government, sparking the Second Red Scare.", "answer": "Joseph \"Joe\" <b><u>McCarthy</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this system\u2019s Bethnal Green locale, over 170 civilians died after the</u></b> <b><u>discharge of anti-aircraft rockets caused a stampede of citizens. A predecessor to this</u></b> <b><u>infrastructure network took ten years for the Metropolitan (+)</u> Railway to build due to its inability to raise money during the Crimean War. A seventh of London\u2019s population lived in this infrastructure network during a period known as (*) </b>\u201cThe Blitz\u201d due to the relative safety of subterranean shelters. For ten points, name this rapid transit network of the Greater London area.", "answer": "London <b><u>Underground</u></b> (accept The <b><u>Tube</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}